Preliminary Guide to the Harold Grier McCurdy Papers, 1918-2006
Harold Grier McCurdy papers 1918-2006
McCurdy, Harold Grier, 1909-
22.6 Linear Feet 9934 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Harold Grier McCurdy Papers was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1989-2010.
Biographical Note
Child psychologist and teacher, poet, professor at the University of North Carolina, and father of artist John Derrickson McCurdy.
Collection Overview
Collection contains an unpublished manuscript of A Photorealist in Quest of God by McCurdy. This work traces the artistic development of his son, John. Among the correspondence are letters between John and his parents, and diaries detailing the early lives of both John and his sister, Ann. Also included is an exhibition catalog of John's work (1977); an essay by John with publishers' responses; his doctoral dissertation; reprints of articles John wrote; original art work; legal papers, handwritten notes, printed material, yearbooks, course work, diplomas, correspondence; and slides and photographs. Other works by Harold McCurdy include Barbara, The Unconscious Autobiography of a Child Genius and About Mary. Another group of materials include correspondence, clippings, articles, and other items relating to Harold McCurdy's writing, teaching, and publishing career.
Addition (2000-0424) (8216 items, dating from 1918-1999) provides a relatively well-rounded and sometimes intimate look into McCurdy's personal and professional life over the majority of his lifetime. Materials include correspondence from and to McCurdy; writings on psychology, poetry, and drama; diaries; subject files; cartoons; and 254 color slides of paintings and other sketches and writings by McCurdy's son, John Derrickson McCurdy.
Addition (2009-0021) (8 items; 0.2 lin. ft.; 1949-2006) consists of 6 bound notebooks and diaries kept by McCurdy. Some of the diaries appear to be sequential; other notebooks include clippings and writings. There is also an index of McCurdy's submissions (1949-1998), as well as a compilation of his poetry (2006).
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
McCurdy, Harold Grier, 1909-
McCurdy, John Derrickson, 1940-1974
Parent and child
Artists -- United States
Artists -- United States -- Correspondence
Color slides
Diaries
Contents of Collection
- Original Collection, 1940-1989, (4 boxes)
  Collection contains an unpublished manuscript of A Photorealist in Quest of God by McCurdy. This work traces the artistic development of his son, John. Among the correspondence are letters between John and his parents, and diaries detailing the early lives of both John and his sister, Ann. Also included is an exhibition catalog of John's work (1977); an essay by John with publishers' responses; his doctoral dissertation; reprints of articles John wrote; original art work; legal papers, handwritten notes, printed material, yearbooks, course work, diplomas, correspondence; and slides and photographs. Other works by Harold McCurdy include Barbara, The Unconscious Autobiography of a Child Genius, and About Mary. Another group of materials include correspondence, clippings, articles, and other items relating to Harold McCurdy's writing, teaching, and publishing career.
  - Accession 1989-0089 (Box Acc. 89/089: Box 1)
  - Accession 1990-0094 (Box Acc. 90/094: Box 1)
  - Accession 1990-0094 (Box Acc. 90/094: Box 2)
  - Accession 1998-0237 (Box Acc. 98/237: Box 1)
- Accession (2000-0424), 1918-1999
  Addition (2000-0424) (8216 items, dating from 1918-1999) provides a relatively well-rounded and sometimes intimate look into McCurdy's personal and professional life over the majority of his lifetime. Materials include correspondence from and to McCurdy; writings on psychology, poetry, and drama; diaries; subject files; cartoons; and 254 color slides of paintings and other sketches and writings by McCurdy's son, John Derrickson McCurdy.
  Box 6 contains sensitive material--student grades. Patrons must sign a release form before use.
  - Correspondence to and from McCurdy and subject files, A-D, 1967-1999 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to and from McCurdy and subject files, E-N, 1966-1999 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence to and from McCurdy and subject files, O-Z, 1941-1999 (Box 3)
  - Poetry and professional writings in manuscript form, 1943-1997, (one binder and various printed journals) (Box 3)
  - Poetry and professional writings in manuscript form, 1943-1997, (15 folders) (Box 4)
  - Letters home, 1929-1932, 1964, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Letters to Frank, 1930-1934, 1987-1992, (four folders) (Box 4)
  - Drawings/cartoons, 1918-1926, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Drawings/cartoons, 1918-1926, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Academic reprints and other writings, mainly poetry and plays, including Realizing Westward, 1940s-1990s (some material in deteriorating bound volumes) (Box 5)
  - Biographical files and publications, 1942-1999 (Box 6)
    Includes student grades-patrons must sign a release form to use.
  - Poetry and professional writings in manuscript form, 1943-1997 (one printed journal) (Box 7)
  - Elegy by W.S.(published book by other author) (Box 7)
  - Bound volume of hand-copied verses by well-known poets (Box 7)
  - Son John McCurdy's biographical material, academic writings and course work, cartoons, sketches, drawings, and lists of paintings, 1940-1974 (Box 7)
    Includes a small amount of material relating to daughter Ann McCurdy
  - Papers, 1965-1970 (Box 8)
  - Manuscript of A Photorealist in Search of God (Box 8)
  - Data books on subjects' dream contents, 1968 and undated, (three volumes) (Box 8)
  - Personal and professional writings, including rough drafts of poems, 1942-1999 (Box 8)
  - Personal and professional writings, including rough drafts of poems, 1942-1999 (Box 9)
  - Copies of poems from other writers (Box 9)
  - Diploma from Duke University, Ph.D., 1938 (Box 9)
  - Loose material from inside diploma, including two sketches by McCurdy, ca. 1940 and undated (Box 9)
  - Dream and daily diaries, 1941-1999 (Box 9)
  - Color slides of John McCurdy's paintings, shows, and wedding, 1965-1987 (Box 10)
  - Oversize artwork (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Oversize Material (Opaperfolder 1)
- Accession (2009-0021), 1949-2006, (2 boxes)
  Addition (2009-0021) (8 items; 0.2 lin. ft.; 1949-2006) consists of 6 bound notebooks and diaries kept by McCurdy. Some of the diaries appear to be sequential; other notebooks include clippings and writings. There is also an index of McCurdy's submissions (1949-1998), as well as a compilation of his poetry (2006).
  - Diary, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Before and After March 23, 1989, notebook of writings and poems
  - Red and black diary with clippings, 1964-1995
  - Composition book V, 1990 (pages 376-474)
  - Composition book IX, 1991-1992 (pages 810-869)
  - Composition book X, 1992 (pages 870-929, 1145-1204)
  - Index 1949-1998 (Box 2)
  - Poetry compilation, 2006